Margaret Wooster Curti Papers, 1898-1963
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Margaret Wooster Curti Papers
1898-1963
Curti, Margaret Wooster, b. 1891
MS 38
6 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Professor and psychologist. Creator of a successful pre-school program at the Peoples' Institute in Northampton, Massachusetts, which evolved into a laboratory for Smith College's child psychology classes. Papers also depict family life in Nebraska and Northampton. Materials include correspondence, research, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, and artwork.
Biographical Note
Margaret Wooster Curti was born in Silver Spring, Nebraska on 18 February 1891, the daughter of Lillie Margaret (Todd) Wooster and Charles Wooster. After graduating from Lincoln (Nebraska) High School in 1908, she attended the University of Nebraska, earning an A.B. in 1913 (Phi Beta Kappa) and an M.A. in psychology in 1915. She went on to the University of Chicago, where she obtained her Ph.D. in 1920.
Curti taught briefly at Mesa High School in Mesa, Arizona and then at Beloit College prior to her appointment in 1922 as Assistant Professor of Psychology at Smith College. While at Beloit, she met historian Merle Eugene Curti; they married in Paris in 1925 while he was studying under a fellowship at The Sorbonne. The couple had two daughters, Nancy Alice, born 3 March 1927, and Martha, born 7 January 1932.
Curti taught at Smith until 1937, during which time she was promoted to Associate Professor. She went on to work as Research Associate in the Teachers' College at Columbia University from 1937 to 1942, and lectured at the University of Wisconsin during the 1943-44 academic year. In 1930, Curti published the book Child Psychology, which was a widely used college textbook for many years. She also wrote for professional journals and lectured at national conferences. Liberal in her politics, Curti was a member of the national Socialist Party and of the Hampshire County Progressive Club in Northampton, Massachusetts. She was also involved in The People's Institute in Northampton and in 1935, in response to the needs of the city's working mothers, she created a successful pre-school program for two- to five-year-olds at the People's Institute, which quickly evolved into a lab for Smith College's child psychology classes as well.
Margaret Wooster Curti died of breast cancer in Madison, Wisconsin on 18 September 1961.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Margaret Wooster Curti Papers consist of 2 linear feet and primarily contain biographical material and correspondence, dating from 1900 to 1961. Types of material include school records; artwork; correspondence; photographs; and published and unpublished monographs and journal articles. The correspondence is extensive and contains letters between Margaret Wooster Curti and her husband, Merle Curti, as well as letters between Curti and her parents and siblings. The photograph album depicts the Wooster and Curti families and their lives in Nebraska and in Northampton, Massachusetts; the scrapbook created by Curti's grandmother depicts the kinds of newspaper clippings that were of interest to an early-nineteenth century girl. Some of Curti's writings about intelligence testing of black and white children may be of interest to scholars, as might a M.S. thesis by Wendy Spotts, titled "Illegitimacy as it Relates to the Physical, Intellectual, and Personality Development of Lower-Class Negro Jamaican Children."
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Margaret Wooster Curti Papers were donated in 1978 by her daughter, Martha Curti, now Mother Felicitas Curti, OSB.
Search Terms
Curti, Margaret Wooster, b. 1891; Curti, Merle Eugene, 1897-1996; Child development--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Child psychology--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Children--Intelligence testing--History--Sources; Family--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Nebraska--History--20th century--Sources; Smith College--Faculty--History-Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
There is related material in the Nebraska Historical Society, notably correspondence between Margaret Wooster Curti and her father, Charles Wooster. Additional professional papers of Margaret Wooster Curti are located at the Archives of the History of American Psychology, the University of Akron, Ohio. Material pertaining to Curti's years on the Smith College faculty are located in the Smith College Archives. The Merle Eugene Curti Papers are located at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Archives Division, Madison, Wisconsin.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL (1900-62), 1 linear ft.
  This series contains basic biographical information about Margaret Wooster Curti and her family. It includes Curti's death certificate, her obituaries, and letters of condolence to Merle Curti; school records; photographs, including an album; a scrapbook created by Curti's grandmother, Nancy Ann Todd; clippings about Margaret and Merle Curti, and about her father, Charles Wooster; several Curti family newsletters; and artwork and special occasion cards created by Margaret Wooster Curti as a child, for her family.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE (1898-1961), .75 linear ft.
  Family correspondence is extensive and includes over twenty years of letters between Margaret Wooster Curti and her husband, Merle Eugene Curti, as well as many years of correspondence between Curti, her siblings and her extended family.
- SERIES III. WRITINGS (1923-63), .25 linear ft.
  This series is comprised of published monographs and journal articles, and typescripts of unpublished essays by Margaret Wooster Curti; it also includes poems by Curti. Wendy Spotts's thesis, "Illegitimacy as it Relates to the Physical, Intellectual, and Personality Development of Lower-Class Negro Jamaican Children," is based in part on unfinished research conducted by Curti on the intelligence of black children and white children in Jamaica, B.W.I.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Obituaries, essays, telegrams, photographs, and clippings, 1927-61, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Education
    - Primary and secondary school: writings and drawings, circa 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lincoln (Nebraska) High School: report cards and graduation invitation, 1906-08 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - University of Nebraska
      - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Commencement program, A.B. degree, mementos, 1915, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Petitions, clippings, and related correspondence, 1913-17, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        [See also Oversize Materials]
      - Essays, 1917, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - University of Chicago: correspondence, and program and script for plays, 1917, 1920, 1930, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Post-graduate employment
    - Mesa High School, Mesa, Arizona: program for play directed by Curti, and Valentine's Day card, 1919, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Beloit College: correspondence, clippings, and pamphlet,1921, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Artwork and special occasion cards for family members
    - To Lillie Margaret Wooster, Charles Wooster, Charles Wooster, Jr., Dorothy Wooster, and Sophia Wooster, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
    - Handmade booklets, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Condolences, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Family
    - Curti, Merle: biographical information, correspondence, clippings and poem, 1944-62, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Curti, Nancy Alice: birth certificate, records of conversations with mother, and typescripts of early poems, 1927-34 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Curti family: holiday letters and family newsletter, 1935-37 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Wooster family: correspondence, family tree, obituaries, essay, clippings, photograph, and poems, 1921-38, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photograph album, circa 1920-32 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook made by Nancy Ann Todd, Margaret Wooster Curti's grandmother, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Book of sheet music, n.d. (Box 4)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Family
    - Brightenberg, Edith Wooster, 1918-54 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Curti, Evla May, 1922-23, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Curti, Martha, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Curti, Merle, 1921-60, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4-9)
    - Curti, Nancy Alice, 1929-41 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Swinney, Sophia Wooster and family, 1913-30 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Swink, Dorothy Wooster, 1906-28 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Wooster, Charles and Lillie Margaret Wooster, 1898-1933, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
    - Wooster, Mildred and family, 1918-1940 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Wooster, Pauline, 1922-47 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified, 1909-61, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Third party
    - Brightenberg, Edith Wooster, 1918, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Wooster, Lillie Margaret, 1913-28 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Friends and acquaintances
    - Hunter, Louis and Trixie, 1932-61 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Neilson, William A., 1931 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Wolfe, Harry Kirk, 1914-18 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Wolfe, Katharine Brandt, 1914-25 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1910-53, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Political, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Professional, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - List of publications, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Published works
    - Book: Child Psychology: publicity, clippings and reviews, 1930-31 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Articles
    - "Certain Factors in the Development of a New Spatial Coordination," Psychological Monographs, Psychological Review Publications, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "The Gesell Schedules Applied to One-, Two- and Three- Year Old Negro Children of Jamaica, B.W.I.," Journal of Comparative Psychology, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "The Intelligence of Delinquents in Light of Recent Research," The Scientific Monthly, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Intelligence Tests of White and Colored School Children in Grand Cayman," The Journal of Psychology, 1960 (Box 6)
    - "Native Fear Responses of White Rats in the Presence of Cats", Psychological Monographs, Psychological Review Publications, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "A Further Report on Fear Responses of White Rats in the Presence of Cats," Journal of Comparative Psychology, 1942 (Box 6)
    - "The New Lombrosianism," Journal of the American Institute of Criminal Law and Criminology, Aug 1926 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "A Preliminary Report on the Testing of Young Maya Children in Yucatan," Journal of Comparative Psychology, Oct 1939 (Box 6)
    - Article in German journal, 1937 (Box 6)
    - Book review: Psychological Bulletin, Jun 1934 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - List of book reviews by Curti, Report of the President of Smith College, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Unpublished works
    - "Does Democracy Work in Wisconsin?," 1957 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - "An Experimental Study of Bright and Dull Children" (M.A. thesis), 1915 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "Relationships Between Goodenough Draw-A-Man Test Performance and Skin Color Among Preadolescent Jamaican Children," n.d. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Poems, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Writings by others
    - Spotts, Wendy S.: M.S. thesis: "Illegitimacy as it Relates to the Physical, Intellectual, and Personality Development of Lower-Class Negro Jamaican Children," 1963 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Daily Nebraskan, 11 Apr 1917 (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Pencil sketch by Myrtle Harris, n.d. (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Application for membership in the Daughters of the American Revolution, Lillie Margaret Wooster, n.d. (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Play program, "The Research Significant", 10 Apr 1910 (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Handmade card to Lillie Margaret Wooster, n.d. (Map-case Flat File:)